This video is sponsored by Card Kingdom.
If you want Magic singles or sealed
product, use my link in the description.
Hi everyone, I'm Nita Honan and in this
video I'm continuing my Reality Fracture
set review. I've already covered all the
multicolored and colorless cards and in
this video we're going to look at all
the white ones. For each of these cards
I'll discuss how I think they'll perform
in limited, that means draft and sealed,
and I'll punctuate each evaluation with
a letter grade. If you're new to my set
reviews and unsure of what my letter
grades mean, you can find a guide in the
description. There are some important
things to keep in mind as I review these
cards. First, because we're only talking
about draft and sealed here, I'm only
going to be talking about cards that can
be found in play boosters. In other
words, cards with the FRA code in the
lower left-hand corner. If you think a
card is missing in this video, it's
probably one of the Commander cards
which have FRC in the lower left-hand
corner. These are also, of course, my
evaluations of these cards before it's
possible to play this new limited format
because my goal is to have this set
review done for you in time for the
pre-release. That means I'm going to be
wrong about some things, but as the
format comes into focus, I'll be doing
videos updating my thoughts on these
cards. Lastly, I want to let you know
that there's some set review related
perks for being a channel member or a
patron. You get access to my ongoing set
notes during preview season, which is
kind of a rough draft of my set review,
and once the set review is complete, you
get a spreadsheet with all of my grades.
If those perks interest you, check out
the description where you can find out
how to support the channel using one of
those methods. All right, without
further ado, let's dive in with a look
at the white cards in Reality Fracture.
First up, we've got Academic Ascent,
which for one generic and a white is a
common instant. Target creature gets
plus two plus two and gains flying until
end of turn, and it has Empower Jace
two. This is the headliner mechanic in
this set. It means that if you don't
control a Jace token, you make one and
put two loyalty counters on it. And if
you already have a Jace token, you just
put two loyalty counters on it. This is
a possible trick with a bit of I swing
for lethal in the air upside, and the
Empower means you'll at least get to
surveil once thanks to this card,
certainly helping its stock. It'll feel
especially good if you already have a
Jace play with like one loyalty counter
cuz it kind of turns this into a
two-for-one of sorts. Empower Jace 2 is
probably not worth a whole card, but
it's worth like 2/3 of one. So, you're
getting a trick that can help your
creature win combat a decent chunk of
the time and some value on top of that.
And that additional value is important.
I think this would be like a C- minus
level trick without Empower Jace, and I
think with it it gives it another angle,
and I think it's enough for it to be a
C.
Next up, it's Blossom
which for three generic and a white is a
2/4 Angel Cleric at common. It's got
flying and vigilance, and it enters
prepared. So, this is the other big
mechanic in the set.
When a creature is prepared, that means
you can cast a copy of its spell, and
anytime you do that, the creature
becomes unprepared. And the spell here
is Seed Suture, which is a green-white
hybrid mana for a sorcery that puts a
plus-one plus-one counter on target
creature, and you gain a life. So, if
this was a five-mana 2/4 with flying and
vigilance it could put a counter
somewhere, including on itself, I'd
think it was a common you play a decent
percentage of the time. And this is much
better than that because you can run it
out on turn four without the prepared
spell if you want to. And then there's
also a plus-one plus-one counter and
life gain synergy in the set, so I think
this is going to end up being a really
nice common, giving it a C+.
Next up, it's Campus Crier, which for
one generic and a white is a 3/1 Human
Advisor at common. You can pay one
generic and exile it from your graveyard
to Empower Jace 2. I'm usually
reasonably happy with a two-mana 3/1
with upside. It hits pretty hard early
in the game, and then later in the game
it can trade up for things with three
toughness, which feels fine. And then
this one can give you a bit of Empower
Jace value from the graveyard. I think
it's a C.
Next up, it's Enlightened Confidant,
which for one generic and a white is a
Kor Cleric at mythic rare. It's a 2/1
with lifelink, and at the beginning of
your instep, if you gained life this
turn, you surveil one. If you put a card
with mana value less than or equal to
the amount of life you gained this turn
into your graveyard this way, put that
card into your hand. This is a cool
white to dark confidant, but I don't
think it's quite as good as its
predecessor. In turns you don't gain
life, it doesn't give you a shot at
getting a card at all, but I do like
that even if you've only gained one
life, like with Seed Suture, you have a
pretty good chance of drawing a card
because it lets you get lands back when
you surveil them, too. And obviously
they have a mana value of zero. This can
fuel itself to a certain extent,
although without any help you sort of
need an empty board in order for this to
get in, trigger life link, and survive
so you get to your end step. I think
it'll just feel like a two mana two one
with life link sometimes, and that's
just not a very good card. This set does
have a significant life gain theme,
especially in green white, but I don't
see you being able to consistently get
an extra card out of this for it to be
insane. It's merely good. I'm giving it
a B minus. Next up it's Fate Shaper
Aspirant, which for four generic into
white is a three four rhino cleric at
common. When it enters you choose one,
return target legendary card from your
graveyard to your hand, or put a plus
one plus one counter on target creature.
It gains vigilance and indestructible
until end of turn. There are a lot of
legendary creatures in this set, so that
mode will certainly come up, and it'll
be useful when you're trying to grind
out a win. The other mode is better when
you're the beatdown already, as it lets
you send in a pretty formidable
attacker, and it getting vigilance is a
pretty big deal. It means you can attack
on almost any board for free with that
creature. I like that these two modes
are generally good in different
situations, and the second mode is
almost always useful. Worst case you can
always put a counter on the Aspirant
itself. Obviously that's not ideal, but
that's the fail case. It is five mana,
it's a little bit clunky, but I think
it's a five mana card you end up running
one of in a lot of your white decks. I'm
giving it a C.
Next up it's Flickering Hound, which for
three generic into white is a two two
dog at rare. Whenever you cast a
creature spell, exile up to one other
target creature you control, then return
that card to the battlefield under its
owner's control. This is kind of a color
shifted Displacer Kitten, and that card
was terrible in limited. This one
probably is, too. This is a card that's
here for people to make use of in
constructed formats. It's not very good
in limited because the stat line is
horrible combined with the fact that you
don't always have something that is
actually worth blinking. Basically, it's
pretty close to worthless in combat and
it has a trigger that, while it has
potential, won't line up to actually be
useful except on very rare occasions in
limited. I'm starting it at a D and it
wouldn't be a surprise to me if it was
worse.
Next up, it's Generous Revival, which
for two generic and a white is an
uncommon sorcery. Return target creature
card with mana value three or less from
your graveyard to the battlefield with
an additional plus and plus one counter
on it and it flashes back for generic
and a white. Even with flashback, I'm
not very into this. I mean, we get one
and two mana ways to reanimate small
creatures. Paying three for a narrow
reanimate, even with the counter and the
ability to cast it again later, doesn't
sound great to me. It can give you a
two-for-one in the long run to be sure,
but it just seems too inefficient in
particular. Giving it a D plus.
Next up, it's Germinate Recruits, which
for two generic and a white is a rare
instant. Create X 2/2 colorless wizard
soldier creature tokens named Cadet,
where X is the amount of life you gained
this turn. Getting enough life for this
to be good and having mana left over is
unfortunately kind of a big ask.
Lifelink is probably the way you get
there the most easily and the good news
is even if you've only gained two life,
this will feel like a good deal. I'm
just worried about the times when you've
gained zero or one life, which even in a
life gain deck is going to happen a
significant percentage of the time. I
think this needs a build around grade
because you need to be really dedicated
to being able to gain large chunks of
life for this to really go off and it's
pretty good when you can and I think
most white decks will get enough out of
it that it's not like completely
unplayable,
but it's probably a D in most white
decks and a B in a life gain deck.
Next up, it's Grafted Surgeon, which for
two generic and a white is a 2/2 human
cleric at common that enters with a plus
and plus one counter on it and when it
dies, you put its counters on up to one
target creature you control. So, this is
a three mana 3/3 with a tiny bit of
upside. I say tiny because pretty much
every card we've seen that dies and puts
its counters somewhere else over the
last several years has been mediocre in
limited. It comes up short, but it's not
the most meaningful death trigger most
of the time, and sometimes you just
don't have another creature around
anyway. I think it's just a C minus.
Next up, it's Guiding Hydra, which for
an X and a white is a 1-0 Hydra Horror
at rare. It enters with X +1 +1 counters
on it, and at the beginning of combat on
your turn, you may remove a +1 +1
counter from this creature. If you do,
put a +1 +1 counter on each other
creature you control. This looks pretty
great to me. It scales all game, and its
counter removal effect is a beginning of
combat trigger, meaning it's very likely
you get value from that trigger the turn
this comes down, and oftentimes it'll
make combat way more advantageous for
you. I think this is going to feel like
a less busted roboroid, and that still
makes for a really good card. It does
take a decent amount of mana and a
somewhat significant board state to
really get going, but I think that'll
line up often enough in white decks that
I think it reaches into the lower bomb
range, giving it an A minus.
Next up, it's Hexhaven Battalion, which
for four generic and two white is a
common sorcery that creates three 2/2
colorless Wizard Soldier creature tokens
named Cadet, and you empower Jace 2, and
it has basic land cycling for two, which
means you can pay two and discard it to
search up a basic land, put in your
hand, and then shuffle. This card
reminds me of Imperial Oath, a card from
Kamigawa: Neon Dynasty that was six mana
to make three 2/2s, and then you scried
three. This probably isn't quite as good
as scry three is usually going to be
better than empower Jace 2, but you will
at least get to surveil once with that.
Then, you throw in the basic land
cycling upside, which means you can
pitch this early if you're mana screwed
and not feeling like you're going to get
to six anytime soon, and I think this
looks like a nice common overall. It
probably won't quite measure up to the
oath, but it's the kind of thing that
adds significantly to your board and
improves your card quality all at once.
I'm giving it a C plus.
Next up, it's Kindred Judgment, which
for five generic and two white is a rare
sorcery. Choose a creature type. Destroy
all creatures that aren't of the chosen
type. This set does not have a
significant Kindred theme, and that's
mostly good news for a card like this
one. That's because you and your
opponent being in the same color pair or
being in one of the same colors doesn't
mean you'll have a bunch of overlapping
creature types. As such, being able to
name a creature type that maximizes
damage to their board and minimizes
damage to yours is very much on the
table. There are going to be times where
you're the only one who controls a
knight or an angel or something like
that, and that means you come out ahead
since your creature will still be on the
board while your opponent's stuff just
gets swept away entirely. There will
still be some awkward moments with this,
but I think most of the time you can
make a choice that turns this into an
asymmetrical wrath, and those are
powerful even at seven mana. I think
it's a bomb. I'm giving it an A.
Next up, it's Loyal Tutor, which for one
white mana is a rare instant. You search
your library for a planeswalker card,
reveal it, then shuffle and put that
card on top. This card completes a very
old cycle of cards that allowed you to
tutor up a card of a specific type or
types and put it on top of your library.
So, now we have a planeswalker one. It's
a cool card and it's a cool callback to
those, but it's terrible in limited.
It's card disadvantage, and there's not
even a very good chance you have a
planeswalker to tutor up anyway. Even if
your deck has one planeswalker in it, I
would advise you not to run this. You
can't really overstate how bad it is to
go down a card just for a tutor effect,
and then you still have to spend all the
mana on your planeswalker. Sure, your
planeswalker's probably really good, but
it's not so good that it's still going
to feel like a great play when you
basically discard a card and spend a
mana just to put it on top of your
library. And then, of course, there's
the occasions where your planeswalker
has been milled or you already have it
in your hand or whatever, and then you
can't tutor it up at all. So, this is
just an F in limited. Most tutors are,
believe it or not, especially ones that
are card disadvantage. For a tutor to be
good in limited, it usually also has to
be a creature or something that impacts
the board in some way, and this doesn't
do it. And like I keep saying, it's also
actively card disadvantage. It's an F.
Next up, it's Memory Trap, which for two
generic and a white is a common
enchantment. When it enters, exile
target nonland permanent opponent
controls until this enchantment leaves
the battlefield. So, here's our usual
Oblivion Ring-like removal spell, and as
usual, it'll be an important common
since it can deal with any non-land
permanent relatively efficiently.
There's always a risk of it getting
removed or something, but the upside is
very real. It's hard for it to feel
insanely efficient in most situations,
and it usually comes out as either a C+
or B- depending on the format. I'm going
to go a little bit on the pessimistic
side here and give it a C+.
Next up, it's Predictive Preparations,
which for one generic and a white is a
common sorcery. Put a +1/+1 counter on
each of one or two target creatures, and
it has flashback for three generic and a
white. The base form of this card isn't
very exciting, but it's not terrible. I
do kind of wish flashing it back gave
you a third counter or something,
though. As is, it sort of feels like it
falls short of giving you six total
mana's worth of value, and it's not the
kind of flashback spell that makes you
feel like you're getting a two-for-one,
either. It's kind of sad because this
card reminds me of Travel Preparations,
a limited all-star from the past, but
it's just so much clunkier than that
was. I think you'd up cutting this a
significant chunk of the time, giving it
a C-.
Next up, it's Prophesied In, which for
one generic and a white is an uncommon
instant. Destroy target creature. If it
wasn't attacking, its controller draws a
card. Two mana to destroy an attacking
creature is a spell that basically
always makes the cut, and this has the
added upside of going after any creature
when it has to. You can also use it on
your own creature to draw a card in a
pinch, although that's a corner case. It
is true that two-for-one-ing yourself
with this isn't always great, but when
you really need an emergency removal
spell, it can do the job. And when
you're just casting it to destroy an
attacking creature, it does a really
good job. I think this is a B.
Next up, it's Refute Destiny, which for
one generic and a white is an uncommon
sorcery. Exile target creature or
planeswalker that's green or blue.
Surveil one. So, this set has a cycle of
color hosers, something we used to see a
lot of, but we don't see very much these
days. They tend to like giving
sideboard-type cards modality that makes
them passable even when the thing they
hit on isn't around, but they didn't
really do that with this cycle and there
are both upsides and downsides to that.
There is a decent chance for any deck to
have a blue planeswalker in play as a
result of Empower Jace, but destroying
that token isn't exactly going to feel
great most of the time. I also wish they
had at least made it so it could exile
up to one target because then you could
at least get the surveil as a fail case
and putting it in your main deck
wouldn't be quite as bad. As is, without
a target this is just uncastable. Now,
when you do run into someone playing
green or even better both, it's great
making it a classic sideboard card.
Putting it in your main deck, you'll run
into enough opponents with targets for
it to be like a D, but against an
opponent with plenty of targets, it
moves up to a B. Next up, it's
Repurposed Enforcer, which for one
generic and a white is a 3/2 human
soldier at rare. When it attacks, you
empower Jace X, where X is the number of
creatures you control. This has good
stats, which will allow it to attack
reasonably well early. While your
Empower won't be the most exciting in
the early game, it is value and it's
great that if you get it later, it can
potentially give you a ton of loyalty
and effectively draw you several cards
if you have the time. This creature does
have to do the attacking and you're not
always going to get to that point, but
sometimes this will put a ton of loyalty
counters on Jace in the mid to late
game, like on a board stalled game, and
that can give you some serious advantage
on the board because you'll end up
drawing a bunch of cards. I think this
is a B.
Next up, it's Return to the Light
Realms, which for seven generic and two
whites a mythic rare sorcery that
returns all nonland permanent cards from
your graveyard to the battlefield. This
is a cool design and a fun callback to
Rise of the Dark Realms, but nine mana
is just too much to consistently get to
in limited. Most of the time, you'll
just never be able to cast this in your
typical game. It's an F.
Next up, it's Shatterwing Pegasus, which
for two generic and a white is a 2/3
Pegasus at common with flying. You can
pay four generic and a white and
creatures you control get +1/+1 until
end of turn. Creatures with a decent
baseline that have this kind of
activated ability always end up being at
least solid for white in limited. It's
just nice having something that's fine
when you curve out that can then pay you
off for curving out with its own
activated ability, which can really
wreak havoc on combat if you've got a
lot of creatures and white often does. I
think this is a C+.
Next up is Surgical Precision, which for
one generic and a white is a common
sorcery. Choose one. Destroy target
creature with toughness four or greater.
You gain a life or you draw a card and
gain two life. Two mana to kill a high
toughness creature usually means you'll
be trading up and when this doesn't have
a target, it can at least replace itself
and both modes will trigger life gain
payoffs. It's a nice common, giving it a
C+. Next up it's Unflinching
Hordemaster, which for one generic and a
white is a 2/1 human cleric at common
with ward one and whenever you gain
life, you put a +1/+1 counter on this
creature. This is a pretty nice take on
a Johnny's Pride mate. Adding ward one
to the mix is nice because your opponent
almost certainly can't spend less mana
to cast this than you did to cast the
Hordemaster. So, you don't ever get like
completely blown out. And then
obviously, that helps it stay in play a
turn longer, you know, because your
opponent's removal spell will cost more.
That means you get more counters on it.
That means it attacks and blocks more.
And then sometimes ward one and your
opponent misses land drops, they just
can't remove it and this thing just
keeps growing. I think it looks like a
nice two drop and I think there's enough
life gain going on in white for it to
grow significantly, giving it a C+.
Next, there's Your Fate Is Here, which
for two generic and a white is an
uncommon instant. Destroy target
creature or planeswalker with mana value
three or greater. Surveil one. So, this
is a good removal spell. You're always
going to at least break even and you're
often going to be able to trade up for
big scary things while also getting a
surveil trigger. That would be a nice
upside to have on this card anyway
because, you know, card quality and
loading your graveyard are both
important things in limited. But, in
this set it might give you some kind of
awesome trigger, too. So, I think this
is a B-.
All right. All right, from here we're
moving to the Echoed Pair cards in the
set that are white. There's a special
Echoed Pair sheet in this set that makes
it so that every pack when you open it
has three cards from the Echoed Pairs
and two of them are matching. So, they
have different set numbers and
everything else, but obviously they're
still white cards in limited, so we're
going to look at them here. Next, it's
Ajani Resolute, who for one generic and
a white is a two loyalty legendary
planeswalker, Ajani, at mythic rare.
When you gain life, you put a loyalty
counter on him. He has a zero ability
that gains you a life. He has a minus
four ability that makes a two-two white
cat soldier creature token named Ajani's
Pride Mate with, whenever you gain life,
put a plus one plus one counter on this
token. And he has a minus 10 that says
you get an emblem with, creatures you
control get plus two plus two. This
Ajani does not feel great in limited,
where mostly he just comes down and
never adds to the board. Since getting
to four loyalty to get a Pride Mate will
take a while, and you need to get to a
five loyalty if you still want to have
Ajani around after that. Otherwise,
you're just getting in Ajani's Pride
Mate with a bunch of extra steps. Now,
this format does have a dedicated life
gain color pair in green-white, and that
does make him a reasonable build around
if you really get there on life gain,
but even in that deck, I'm not ultra
confident you'll be able to get his
loyalty up high enough to make a Pride
Mate, but at least you'll have a
fighting chance. And once you do that,
and you can keep Ajani around, you'll
feel pretty good about the investment.
He gets a loyalty counter for each
instance of life gain, so if you can do
it multiple times in a turn, his own
zero ability can conceivably raise his
loyalty quickly
alongside those other sources. I think
he's probably just an F in your typical
white deck in the format though, and a
C+ if you're really good at gaining
life. Just not having a way to add to
the board until he gets two more loyalty
is a pretty big problem.
Next up, it's Danitha, Sword of Hope,
who for two generic and a white is a
two-two legendary human knight at
uncommon. She's got first strike.
Whenever you cast an equipment spell or
a spell that targets a creature you
control, you draw a card. This ability
triggers only once each turn. A
three-mana two-two with first strike is
hard to attack into in the early game,
and this can certainly draw you some
cards. Still, the three-mana two-two
stat line without an interest trigger
has not performed well in limited in
quite some time, even when a card has
this amount of upside. It's hard to go
above a C here.
Next up, it's Ghalta, the Immovable, who
for eight generic and a white is a 0/7
legendary elder dinosaur at uncommon. It
costs X less to cast, where X is the
greatest toughness among creatures you
control. Creatures you control can
attack as though they didn't have
defender, and each creature you control
with toughness greater than its power
assigns combat damage equal to its
toughness rather than its power. This is
alternate reality Ghalta is pretty cool.
I like that they flipped it to caring
about toughness, and it is effectively a
7/7. Casting it for five or six mana
seems doable, and there's a chance that
it augments the rest of your board, too.
All that said, this set does not have a
super prominent high toughness theme.
Ghalta is unique in that sense, and that
makes it hard to see this working out
consistently. It's a build-around, but
one I'm so skeptical of I don't even
want to give it a build-around grade
because I don't think you'll be
successful all that often when you do.
It also has a horrendous baseline, like
when you don't have a creature with some
significant toughness on the board. I'm
going to start it at a D plus, but deep
down I really hope it ends up being a
legit build-around because it is a cool
card.
Next up, it's Gideon's Memorial, which
for one generic and a white is a rare
legendary artifact. Creature tokens you
control get plus one plus zero and have
vigilance. You can tap it for one mana
of any color, but you can spend that
mana only to cast a planeswalker spell.
You can pay one generic and a white and
discard this card, and it deals four
damage to target attacking or blocking
creature. This has a lot of little
things going on. Let's start with the
last ability because it's the one that
makes this into a reasonable removal
spell as a baseline, and I think that's
honestly the way you're going to use it
the most in limited. That's about a C
minus or C level removal spell in
limited, but it's nice to have a medium
removal spell that can also buff all of
your tokens. And in a pinch, on
occasion, maybe it helps you splash an
off-color planeswalker. Not going to
happen a lot cuz the planeswalkers are
all higher rarity that you actually have
to pay mana for, and it's not amazing.
Like if you couldn't discard this to be
a removal spell, it might just be an F,
but I think the whole package is a C B
Next up, it's Karn of the Homestead, who
for two generic and a white is a 2/3
legendary human citizen at uncommon.
Whenever a land you control enters, you
gain a life. Whenever a planes you
control enters, you put a plus one plus
one counter on target creature. I like
this design because if you aren't
running a bunch of planes, he's a
passable card as a three mana 2/3 that
gains you life. In a format lots of
payoffs for gaining life. Obviously, he
gets even better in a deck that can run
10 plus planes as that trigger can
definitely do a lot of work over the
course of the game. And I think if you
can do it, you probably wait to play him
until turn four, especially if you have
a planes in your hand and then you play
him and then you play a planes and get a
counter out of him immediately, at which
point you're going to feel good about
what you're getting back. I think he has
a reasonable floor and a pretty high
ceiling. I'm giving him a B minus. Next
up, it's Liliana, the Faultless, who for
one white mana is a 1/1 legendary human
cleric at rare. Whenever another
creature or planeswalker you control
enters, you gain a life. You can pay one
generic, tap her, and discard a card,
and another target creature or
planeswalker you control gains hexproof
until end of turn. We've seen little one
drops out there that give you incidental
life gain work pretty nicely, even in
sets without a life gain theme. So, I
think Liliana will perform quite well
here, especially because she can also
protect your other creatures if you have
mana and cards available. And that's not
asking much because she only wants you
to have one mana up. She'll give you way
more than one mana's worth of value most
of the time if you can run her out on
turn one. And then she has synergy in
the set. So, I think she looks quite
good on the whole. I'm giving her a B
plus.
Next up, it's Lyra, Archangel of Dawn,
who for two generic and a white is a 3/3
legendary angel knight at rare. It has
flying. Whenever you gain life, you put
a plus one plus one counter on each
angel you control. A three mana 3/3
flyer is still a pretty good stat line.
And this format has enough life gain to
imagine that she'll grow. And there are
a few other angels in the set. Not a lot
of them. It's not a huge theme, so
she'll mostly grow herself, but on
occasion you'll have something else that
gets a counter. I'm giving this a B
plus.
Next up, it's Rescue Girl, First
Responder, which for two generic and a
white is a 1/3 legendary human cleric at
uncommon. It's got flying and you can
tap it to return another target
permanent you control to its owner's
hand. Activate only during your turn.
Well, Massacre Girl is a bit different
in this alternate reality and I don't
think very good in limited. A three-mana
1/3 flyer is a bad starting point and
this activated ability, while useful in
the exact right spots, like for
re-buying an interest trigger or saving
a creature from removal, is severely
limited when you can use it, making it a
lot worse and harder to get value out of
it. You can only bounce permanents
during your turn. You can do it at
instant speed at least, but again, only
during your turn. It is nice you can
bounce any permanent you control.
Sometimes that lets you get a little
more value out of it, but I just think
the floor is so bad and that the ceiling
really isn't that impressive. I think
she's a D.
Next up it's Saheeli, Consul of
Oversight, who for three generic and two
white is a 4/4 legendary human advisor
at uncommon. She's got flying. Whenever
you scry or surveil, you create a 1/1
colorless Thopter artifact creature
token with flying. This ability triggers
only once each turn. In most sets, I
would say it's going to be hard to
trigger her the turn she comes down
since you have to spend five mana on
her, but in this format it's far more
likely than normal thanks to Empowered
Jace. So, a not insignificant percentage
of the time you can play her and then
surveil with Jace and get your Thopter
immediately. And things only get way
worse from your opponent from there.
There going to be times where I'm
nervous about running out my five mana
4/4 flyer for sure as my opponent can
find a way to efficiently deal with her
before I ever get a chance to make a
Thopter, but I think the heavy presence
of surveil in this set plus the general
upside she brings is enough for her to
be pretty good. I'm starting her at a B.
Next up it's Teo, Lightshield Expert,
who for one generic and a white is a 1/1
legendary human cleric at uncommon. He's
got flash. When he enters, target
permanent you control gains hexproof
until end of turn. Put a plus and plus
one counter on it if it's a creature.
Put a loyalty counter on it if it's a
planeswalker. This can target itself, so
the floor is a two-mana 2/2 with flash
that works with plus and plus one
counter synergies. That's probably like
a D level card, but that's the fail
case. You're you're to feel a lot better
about flashing in Teo to protect one of
your creatures from removal or to help
it win combat out of nowhere. I mean,
sometimes putting a loyalty counter on
your Jace so that you can draw a card
immediately is worth doing, too. I think
he's a C plus.
Next up, it's Thalia, the Survivor, who
for three generic and a white is a 3/4
legendary human soldier at uncommon.
She's got lifelink and non-creature
spells your opponents cast cost one
generic more to cast. The fact they made
this asymmetrical is pretty nasty and
definitely going to make your opponent
removing her or your other creatures a
lot less efficient. And she has a nice
body that comes with lifelink, too. So,
she's no slouch when it comes to
attacking and blocking and she's a great
place to put counters or equipment and
she can really disrupt some opponents,
giving her a B minus.
Next up, it's Tomik, Orzhov Lawmage, who
for one generic and a white is a 2/1
legendary human advisor at uncommon.
It's got flying. Planeswalkers you
control have no more than one creature
can attack this planeswalker each
combat. And you can also tap Tomik and
target creature with a plus one plus one
counter on it gains flying until end of
turn. A two-minute 2/1 flyer always
feels nice as a turn two play in an
aggro deck and Tomik brings some other
relevant upside to the mix once he's no
longer a great attacker. He's going to
make it harder for your opponent to take
down your Jaces in combat. I think
that's somewhat negligible, but what
isn't is his ability to tap and give
something else with a plus one plus one
counter on it flying, because eventually
your two-man and 2/1 flyer is going to
run into a board where it can no longer
attack because it's not that big and
something with reach or flying will come
down a little bit later. And once you
reach that point, you can just say, "All
right, I'm going to send it this into
the air instead." And it'll be a much
better attacker. This was like a B minus
to me. Next up, it's Way of the Healer,
which is three generic and a white for
an uncommon legendary enchantment. When
it enters, you empower Jace five and
planeswalkers you control have minus
two, create a 2/2 colorless wizard
soldier creature token named Cadet,
surveil one. This looks pretty good to
me. So, you'll get the 2/2 and surveil
one the turn it comes down. That's going
to be the ideal thing to do nine times
out of 10. And then Jace still has three
loyalty on him assuming he wasn't around
at all. And if he is around on the next
turn, you can then either draw a card or
make another soldier. And those soldiers
also make it harder for your opponent to
attack him in the first place. So,
some of these ways I'm a little bit
skeptical of because they don't ever do
anything that actually lets you add to
the board. This one does, and it does it
up front, and it does it for a pretty
small amount of loyalty. And once Jace
has this ability, like all your empower
cards get way better because adding a
2/2 to the board and surveilling one is
generally better than drawing a card in
your typical limited game. This looks
like a B to me. I think it's going to
have the kind of value you expect from
like a saga that makes a couple of
tokens. I think that's what it's going
to feel like a lot of the time. Next,
there's Way of the Mentor, which for two
generic and a white is an uncommon
legendary enchantment. When it enters,
you empower Jace five. And whenever you
gain life, you put a loyalty counter on
each planeswalker you control. I'm less
enthused with this one. This mostly just
empowers five and doesn't give you a way
to add to the board. Sure, he makes it
so your planeswalkers can get loyalty
significantly more often if you're in
like the green-white deck, especially,
but that's pretty narrow and it doesn't
strike me as terribly useful. Jace's
abilities are still just surveil one and
draw a card, and while those things are
good, they're not things that can ever
add to the board. So, getting a bunch of
loyalty on him and playing this card
that also doesn't add to the board all
ends up with a combination that I really
don't like. It's going to feel like a
three-mana enchantment that draws you a
card when it enters a lot of the time,
and it's also going to be a lot harder
for Jace to still exist on your next
turn because you just played a card that
didn't add to the board at all. So, it's
hard to count on getting anything else
out of this empower Jace five, and that
doesn't sound very good to me. I'm
giving it a D+.
Next, it's Yoshimaru, Beloved Companion,
who for two generic and a white is a 2/2
legendary dog at uncommon. If one or
more +1/+1 counters would be put on a
creature you control, that many +1/+1
counters are put on it instead. And you
can pay six generic to put a +1/+1
counter on target legendary creature. I
really hate the three-mana 2/2 stat line
and how poorly it tends to line up
against removal and cheap creatures, you
know, cheaper than three mana. And I
hate it when you have to wait a whole
turn to ever get anything out of the
card, and you're not even guaranteed to
get anything out of this card on your
next turn unless you already have
something that gives you a counter or
you have the mana to use his ability,
which he can use on himself, but still
it's the kind of ability only use when
you're desperate and have nothing else
to do. It's not like it's super
powerful. It's an okay late game mana
sink, but Yoshimaru's going to feel like
a real liability in the early game. And
while I like augmenting my counters and
all that, I just think he's too
inefficient on the whole, giving him a D
plus.
Next up is Yuriko, Blade of the Mighty,
who for three generic and a white is a
2/3 legendary human samurai at uncommon.
During combat, players can't cast spells
or activated abilities that aren't mana
abilities. Whenever a creature you
control attacks a player alone, it gains
double strike until end of turn.
Notably, that first ability is
symmetrical, and that is very awkward in
limited where you usually, you know,
want to use combat tricks. And also, if
your opponent can interact with your
creature during combat, they can
probably interact with it before combat
too in most cases. So, I don't love that
or the stat line. The attack trigger can
be online immediately and sometimes
it'll give you a great attack you didn't
otherwise have, but I think the rest of
what's going on here just isn't enough
for this to be an especially good card
in limited that makes the cut in your
deck consistently, giving it a D plus.
There is also one white special guest
card. These are super rare cards. One
appears in every 55 booster packs. There
are 10 of them total, and we're looking
at one in this particular video because
it's white, and that is Austere Command,
which for four generic and two white is
a sorcery and you choose two: destroy
all artifacts, destroy all enchantments,
destroy all creatures with mana value
three or less, destroy all creatures
with mana value four or greater. So, at
worst, this is a six-mana wrath where
you just choose the last two options.
That's not amazing, you know, it's
clunky as a sorcery and your opponent
gets to rebuild before you do, and it's
awkward in a lot of spots unless you're
really far behind, but those aren't the
only options. You can make choices here
that end up impacting your opponent in a
bigger way than you get impacted, kind
of like that Kindred board sweeper we
were talking about. Like if your
opponent's most problematic creatures
are big, you can destroy all the big
creatures. If their most problematic
creatures are small, you can destroy the
small ones while holding on to your big
creatures. You can choose to blow up
artifacts or enchantments if your
opponent has a great thing going on with
either of those. So, I think this is a
bomb. I think you can make it
asymmetrical often enough for it to be
incredibly strong, and then it has a
floor of being a six-mana wrath, which
while awkward is a pretty good floor to
have. So, those are all the white cards
in Reality Fracture. In the next video,
I'll look at all the blue ones. If you
enjoyed this video, don't forget to like
it and share it so that others can enjoy
it, too. If you want to make sure you
catch future videos, don't forget to
subscribe. And if you want to catch up
on the set review videos that are
already out there, you should see a
playlist on your screen shortly. Thanks
for watching.